Finding Aid for William C. Weber Papers 1858-1940
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Christian Weber Papers 1858-1940
Weber, William Christian (1852-1952)
86260 AC Aa 2
Detroit, Michigan businessman and civic leader. Business correspondence relating to Weber's activities as a dealer in timber lands, his role as a member of the Art Commission in the development of Detroit, Michigan's Cultural Center, his involvement in the construction of the Detroit-Windsor bridge and tunnel and his activities during World War I; and correspondence and class notes of his sons, Harry B. and Erwin W. Weber, while attending University of Michigan; also photographs, including family portraits, aerial views of Windsor, Ontario, and Detroit, photographs of the construction of the Detroit-Windsor Tunnel and Ambassador Bridge, and glass negatives of family vacations in Upper Michigan, Ontario, and Quebec; and maps of land and timber holdings
28 linear feet in 30 boxes
15 oversize volumes
15 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Harry D. Weber, William C. Weber's daughter-in-law (donor 4727 ) to the University of Michigan Library (donor 1278 ) in about 1969. It was thereafter transferred to the Michigan Historical Collections.
The collection is open for research.
William C. Weber, a life-time resident of Detroit, was a land dealer in Michigan involved in lumber and minerals, as well as the owner of land in Detroit and the Border Cities (later Windsor, Ontario). Weber and his wife Emma (Behr) had two sons, Harry (born in 1888) and Erwin (born in 1892). Both sons went to the University of Michigan: Harry attended from 1907 to 1909 when he left to become his father's partner; Erwin attended from 1912 until graduation in 1916. Harry died in 1967. He and his wife Helen (who died in 1973) left no children. Erwin died in 1918 at the Great Lakes Naval Training Center from influenza.
In the first two decades of the century, Weber was involved in cultural events in Detroit, especially the development of the Cultural Center of the city of Detroit on Woodward Avenue. He and Joseph L. Hudson were the chief financial backers of the Art Commission's acquisition of the land on which the Main Library and Detroit Institute of Arts now stand. After Hudson's death in 1912, Weber became embroiled in a controversy over the design of the Cultural Center, failing, however, to sway other members of the commission to his position.
In the twenties and early thirties, Weber was interested in the construction of the Detroit-Windsor bridge and tunnel primarily because he held property in the Border Cities located strategically near the Canadian side of the bridge and near the industrial development of that area. During these years, he also was negotiating with the Ford Motor Company over land deals and the development of mineral lands in Michigan.
The William C. Weber papers are arranged in five series William C. Weber, Erwin C. Weber, and Harry B. Weber, Photographs and Maps. The William C. Weber series is further arranged in seven subseries:
William C. Weber papers
Correspondence, 1858-1940 -- Box 1-15
Letterbooks, 1878-1931 -- Box 16-18
Business and Property Records, ca. 1880-1934 -- Box 18
Papers Relating to the Detroit Cultural Center -- Box 19-20 and Outsize
Papers Relating to Detroit-Windsor Tunnel and Ambassador Bridge
Land and Timber Records, 1870s- ca. 1920? -- Box 20-23
Record of Land Purchases and Taxes, 1868-1928 -- Outsize
Miscellaneous, ca. 1870s-1914 -- Box 23
Erwin C. Weber papers, 1900-1918 -- Box 24
Harry B. Weber papers, 1906-1934 -- Box 25
Photographs -- Box 26-30
Maps (Outsize
The William C. Weber papers cover 28 linear feet (30 boxes), outsize folders, and 15 outsize volumes. Besides information on timber and mineral lands in Michigan, the important aspects of the Weber papers include information on the development of the Cultural Center of Detroit and Weber's very controversial role in it, items on the Detroit-Windsor bridge and tunnel and the development of the Border Cities, and the papers of his two sons, especially the letters they wrote as students at the University of Michigan and their class notes and examinations.
There is one foot of materials related to the Cultural Center (Box 19 and outsize folders) and another of the Detroit-Windsor Tunnel and Ambassador Bridge (Box 20 and outsize folders).
Architectural site plans and property maps of the Detroit Cultural Center are also found in the outsize unbound material.
The collection includes maps relating to Weber's his land holdings in northern Michigan and Windsor, Ontario, including maps of land survey, of timber estimates, and tax and title status for Michigan lands, maps of Windsor subdivisions, maps of coal mining region around Caryville, Tennessee and property maps of the Detroit Cultural Center.
Subjects:
Ambassador Bridge (Detroit, Mich. and Windsor, Ont.); Behr family.; Big Bay Lumber Company.; Business records.; Canada.; Detroit Arts Commission.; Detroit (Mich.). Cultural Center.; Detroit-Windsor Tunnel (Detroit, Mich. and Windsor, Ont.); Ford Motor Company.; German Americans--Michigan.; Hudson, Joseph Lowthian, 1846-1912.; Land use--Michigan.; Logging--Michigan.; Marquette County (Mich.); Mines and mineral resources--United States.; Municipal government--Michigan--Detroit.; Ortmann, Charles L., b. 1830.; Rothschild, Sigmund, 1837-1907.; Section Two Mining Company.; Tennessee.; Tunnels.; University of Michigan--Students--Correspondence.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.; Weber, William Christian, 1853-1952.; Weber family.; Windsor (Ont.); World War, 1914-1918.; Weber, Erwin William, 1892-1918.; Weber, Harry Behr, 1889-1969.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ambassador Bridge (Detroit, Mich. and Windsor, Ont.); Belle Isle (Detroit, Mich.); Bridges.; Camping.; Canada.; Construction industry.; Detroit (Mich.)--Panoramic views.; Detroit-Windsor Tunnel (Detroit, Mich. and Windsor, Ont.); Farms.; Fraternities and sororities.; Georgian Bay (Ont.); Hancock (Mich.); Holmes Literary Society (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Houghton (Mich.); Huron Mountain Club.; Interiors--Fraternities and sororities.; Iron industry.; Iron mining.; Ishpeming (Mich.); Mackinac Island (Mich.); Marquette County (Mich.); Mining.; New York (N.Y.); Quarrying.; Recreation.; Ships--Great Lakes.; Phi Mu Alpha Sinfonia Fraternity of America. Epsilon Chapter (University of Michigan); Superior, Lake.; Tunnels.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1901-1910.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; University of Michigan--Student housing--1901-1910.; University of Michigan--Student housing--1911-1920.; Weber, Erwin William, 1892-1918.; Weber, Harry Behr, 1889-1969.; Weber, William Christian, 1853-1952.; Weber family.
Subject Terms - Maps:
Alcona County (Mich.)--Maps.; Alger County (Mich.)--Maps.; Antrim County (Mich.)--Maps.; Arenac County (Mich.)--Maps.; Baraga County (Mich.)--Maps.; Bay County (Mich.)--Maps.; Caryville (Tenn.)--Maps.; Charlevoix County (Mich.)--Maps.; Cheboygan County (Mich.)--Maps.; Chippewa County (Mich.)--Maps.; Clare County (Mich.)--Maps.; Crawford County (Mich.)--Maps.; Delta County (Mich.)--Maps.; Detroit (Mich.). Cultural Center.; Dickinson County (Mich.)--Maps.; Emmet County (Mich.)--Maps.; Forests and forestry--Michigan--Maps.; Gladwin County (Mich.)--Maps.; Gogebic County (Mich.)--Maps.; Grand Rapids and Indiana Railway Company--Maps.; Houghton County (Mich.)--Maps.; Iosco County (Mich.)--Maps.; Iron County (Mich.)--Maps.; Isabella County (Mich.)--Maps.; Kalkaska County (Mich.)--Maps.; Keweenaw County (Mich.)--Maps.; Luce County (Mich.)--Maps.; Marquette County (Mich.)--Maps.; Midland County (Mich.)--Maps.; Mines and mineral resources--Tennessee--Maps.; Missaukee County (Mich.)--Maps.; Ogemaw County (Mich.)--Maps.; Ontonagon County (Mich.)--Maps.; Oscoda County (Mich.)--Maps.; Otsego County (Mich.)--Maps.; Presque Isle County (Mich.)--Maps.; Real property--Michigan--Maps.; Real property--Michigan--Detroit--Maps.; Real property--Ontario--Windsor--Maps.; Roscommon County (Mich.)--Maps.; Schoolcraft County (Mich.)--Maps.; Windsor (Ont.)--Maps.
Genre/Form:
Architectural drawings.; Aerial photographs--Michigan--Detroit.; Albums.
Glass photonegatives.; Photographs.; Maps.
- William C. Weber papers
  - Correspondence
    The correspondence is organized chronologically and runs from 1858 to 1940 (Boxes 1-17). Business and personal correspondence is interfiled. Among the topics found in this file are Weber's land dealings, the Cultural Center, activities of family members and associates in Germany during and after World War I, and business correspondence of Harry Weber.
    - 1858-1887, 31 folders (Box 1)
    - 1888-April 1893, 29 folders (Box 2)
    - May 1893-1898, 40 folders (Box 3)
    - 1899-1901, 36 folders (Box 4)
    - 1902-October 1903, 43 folders (Box 5)
    - November 1903-October 1905, 40 folders (Box 6)
    - November 1905-July 1907, 37 folders (Box 7)
    - August 1907-September 1909, 44 folders (Box 8)
    - October 1909-March 1911, 39 folders (Box 9)
    - April 1911-September 1912, 32 folders (Box 10)
    - October 1912-August 1914, 32 folders (Box 11)
    - September 1914-May 1918, 41 folders (Box 12)
    - June 1918-December 1922, 42 folders (Box 13)
    - 1923-1926, 45 folders (Box 14)
    - 1927-1940 undated, 36 folders (Box 15)
  - Letterbooks
    - February 2, 1878-June 25, 1903, 15 volumes (Box 16)
    - June 25, 1903-May 14, 1934, 9 volumes (Box 17)
    - circa 1910-1921 (Box 18)
    - circa 1922-1938 (Box 18)
    - 1924-1931 (Box 18)
  - Business and Property Records
    - Description of Weber property in mortgage proposal 1934 (Box 18)
    - Ford Motor Company correspondence relating to Upper Peninsula lands 1916-1939, 14 folders (Box 18)
    - Ford Motor Company miscellanea (Box 18)
    - Inventory of Big Bay Lumber Company property 1910s (Box 18)
      (including buildings and equipment)
    - Inventory of Weber's lands
      - 1890s? (Box 18)
      - May 1914 (Box 18)
      - June 1930 (Box 18)
    - Legal papers, Timothy and James Jerome v. Charles Ortman and Sigmund Rothschild 1880s (Box 18)
    - Mining reports
      - Arizona (Box 18)
      - Colorado (Box 18)
      - Idaho (Box 18)
      - Mexico (Box 18)
      - Montana (Box 18)
      - New Mexico (Box 18)
      - Ontario (Box 18)
      - Tennessee (Box 18)
      - Washington (Box 18)
    - Journals
      - January 1880-February 1883 (Volume 1)
        [1]
      - Vol. A October 1882-April 1898 (Volume 2)
        [2]
      - Vol. B June 1898-August 1911 (Volume 3)
        [3]
      - Vol. C September 1910-April 1918 (Volume 4)
        [4]
    - Ledgers
      - 1877-1882 (Volume 5)
        [5]
      - Vol. A 1882-1908 (Volume 6)
        [6]
      - Vol. B 1910-1916 (Volume 7)
        [7]
  - Papers relating to the Detroit Cultural Center
    There is one foot of materials related to the Cultural Center (Box 19 and outsize folders) which documents Weber's role as a founder and trustee of the Cultural Center. the subseries includes files on the acquisition of the land for the site of the Center, the design competition, trustees minutes, a variety of financial and legal records, and outsize architectural site plans and property maps.
    - Art museum floor plans (Box 19)
    - Arts Commission
      - Papers relating to incorporation (Box 19)
      - Resolutions (Box 19)
    - Belle Isle development (Box 19)
    - Design competition for art museum (Box 19)
    - Legal papers relating to property acquisition
      - undated 1908-1912 (Box 19)
      - 1914-1919 (Box 19)
    - Money donated and expended in purchase of property (Box 19)
    - Museum of Art
      - Financial record 1910 (Box 19)
      - Publications (Box 19)
      - Reports 1914 (Box 19)
      - Trustees minutes 1911-1916 (Box 19)
    - Museum of Art v. George Engel legal papers (Box 19)
    - Museum of Art v. William C. and Emma L. Weber legal papers (Box 19)
    - Newspaper clippings
      - Museum as city property (Box 19)
      - Plans for museum (Box 19)
      - Property acquisition (Box 19)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 19)
    - Public Library plan (Box 19)
    - Statement to Board of Trustees circa 1912 (Box 19)
    - Weber pamphlet 1908 (Box 19)
    - Weber pamphlet 1913 (Box 19)
    - Weber's notes, 8 folders
    - Detroit Cultural Center architectural site plans and property maps (Folder 1)
      (shelved in basement map cases)
  - Papers relating to Windsor property and the Detroit-Windsor tunnel and bridge
    The Detroit-Windsor Tunnel and Ambassador Bridge papers (Box 20 and outsize folders) relate to Weber's property holdings in Windsor and development of the Windsor Tunnel and the Ambassador Bridge.
    - Newspaper clippings relating to tunnel and bridge (Box 20)
    - Papers relating to growth potential and land prices (Box 20)
    - Papers relating to tunnel (Box 20)
    - Papers relating to Weber lands, 4 folders (Box 20)
    - Printed materials relating to development potential (Box 20)
    - Printed materials relating to tunnel and bridge (Box 20)
    - Proposals relating to Weber's tunnel property (Box 20)
    - Weber's notes, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Scrapbook relating to Canadian development (Box 20)
    - Clippings relating to the Detroit-Windsor bridge and tunnel (Folder 2)
  - Land and Timber Records
    The Land and Timber Records subseries includes four feet (Boxes 20-23 and outsize folders) and 15 outsize volumes relate to Weber's land holdings. Chief among the land records are maps of Weber's holdings, compiled land purchase and tax records, and estimates of timber on Weber lands. The timber estimates are especially valuable as they contain detailed descriptions, and in many cases maps, of ground cover, environmental conditions, and cultural features on large tracts of land throughout northern Michigan.
    - Plat books of Weber's Lower Peninsula lands 1880s (Box 20)
    - Printed land sale lists (Box 20)
    - Printed lumber price lists 1912-1918 (Box 20)
    - Section Two Mining Company records 1912-1917 (Box 20)
      (located in Marquette County, Michigan)
    - Timber estimates of Michigan lands
      - Alcona County
        - 1870s (Box 20)
        - 1890s (Box 20)
      - Alger County
        - 1870s (Box 20)
        - 1880s, 2 folders (Box 20)
        - 1890s (Box 20)
        - 1900s (Box 20)
        - 1910s (Box 20)
      - Antrim County
        - 1870s (Box 20)
        - 1880s (Box 20)
      - Arenac County
        - 1870s, 2 folders (Box 21)
        - 1880s (Box 21)
        - 1890s (Box 21)
      - Baraga County
        - 1880s, 2 folders (Box 21)
        - 1890s (Box 21)
        - 1900s, 2 folders (Box 21)
        - 1910s (Box 21)
        - 1920s (Box 21)
      - Bay County
        - 1870s, 2 folders (Box 21)
        - 1880s (Box 21)
      - Charlevoix County
        - 1870s (Box 21)
        - 1880s (Box 21)
      - Cheboygan County
        - 1870s (Box 21)
        - 1880s (Box 21)
      - Chippewa County 1880s (Box 21)
      - Clare County 1870s (Box 21)
      - Crawford County
        - 1870s, 2 folders (Box 21)
        - 1880s, 2 folders (Box 21)
      - Delta County
        - 1880s (Box 21)
        - 1900s (Box 21)
      - Emmet County 1870s (Box 21)
      - Gladwin County
        - 1870s (Box 21)
        - 1880s (Box 21)
      - Iosco County
        - 1870s (Box 21)
        - 1880s (Box 21)
        - 1890s (Box 21)
      - Iron County
        - 1880s (Box 21)
        - 1900s (Box 21)
      - Isabella County 1870s (Box 21)
      - Kalkaska County
        - 1870s (Box 21)
        - 1880s (Box 21)
      - Keweenaw County 1880s (Box 21)
      - Luce County 1880s (Box 21)
      - Marquette County
        - 1870s (Box 22)
        - 1880s, 2 folders (Box 22)
        - 1890s, 2 folders (Box 22)
        - 1900s, 9 folders (Box 22)
        - 1910s, 2 folders (Box 22)
        - 1920s (Box 22)
      - Midland County 1870s (Box 22)
      - Missaukee County
        - 1870s (Box 22)
        - 1880s (Box 22)
        - 1890s (Box 22)
        - 1900s (Box 22)
      - Ogemaw County
        - 1870s, 2 folders (Box 23)
        - 1880s (Box 23)
        - 1890s, 2 folders (Box 23)
      - Ontonagon County 1880s (Box 23)
      - Oscoda County
        - 1870s (Box 23)
        - 1880s (Box 23)
        - 1890s (Box 23)
      - Otsego County
        - 1870s (Box 23)
        - 1880s, 2 folders (Box 23)
        - 1890s (Box 23)
      - Presque Isle County
        - 1890s (Box 23)
        - 1900s (Box 23)
      - Roscommon County
        - 1870s, 2 folders (Box 23)
        - 1880s, 2 folders (Box 23)
        - 1900s (Box 23)
      - Schoolcraft County
        - 1880s (Box 23)
        - 1890s (Box 23)
        - 1900s (Box 23)
      - Grand Rapids & Indiana lands 1880s (Box 23)
      - Miscellaneous
        - 1870s (Box 23)
        - 1880s (Box 23)
    - Timber report, California (Box 23)
    - Miscellanea (Box 23)
  - Record of land purchases and taxes
    - 1876-1941 (Volume 8)
      [8]
    - Plat book of northern Michigan lands 1868-1876 (Volume 1)
      (lands of Charles Ortmann and others) [chiefly maps]
    - Record of lands in Michigan, Vol. A 1869-1886 (Volume 2)
      (record of partnership of William C. Weber and Sigmund Rothschild) [includes maps]
    - Record of lands in Michigan, Vol. B 1871-1891 (Volume 3)
      [includes maps]
    - Upper Peninsula lands of Charles Ortmann, Sigmund Rothschild, and Isaac Rosenwald 1873-1903 (Volume 9)
      [includes maps] [9]
    - U.P., Vol. I 1911-1928 (Volume 10)
      [not exclusively Upper Peninsula lands, also includes Ontario property; includes maps] [10]
    - U.P., Vol. II 1911-1928 (Volume 11)
      [not exclusively Upper Peninsula lands, also includes Ontario property; includes maps] [11]
  - Miscellaneous
    - C. Behr autograph book 1840s (Box 23)
    - Emma Behr autograph book 1873-1877 (Box 23)
    - "A Resume" 1914 (Box 23)
      (publication by Marie Rominger relating to Germany and World War I)
    - Charles F. Weber patent (Box 23)
    - Christian A. Weber copybooks 1870s (Box 23)
- Erwin W. Weber papers
  The Erwin W. Weber series consists of letters, 1912-1918, to and from Weber primarily from his days as a student at the University of Michigan. Letters from his parents are filed in the William C. Weber Correspondence. The series also includes a number of course notebooks and examinations from classes taught by prominent UM faculty members, including Charles Horton Cooley, William Hobbs, Robert Mark Wenley, and Claude Van Tyne.
  - Correspondence 1912-1918, 7 folders (Box 24)
  - Class notes and examinations
    - Sociology 19: Principles of sociology (Charles Horton Cooley) 1914 (Box 24)
    - History 14: Political and constitutional history of the U.S. (Claude Van Tyne), 1914 (Box 24)
    - Philosophy 1: Introduction to philosophy (Robert Mark Wenley) 1914 (Box 24)
    - Rhetoric 12: Essays, readings and discussions (Lyman Bryson) 1914 (Box 24)
    - Geology: Introductory geology (William Hobbs) 1914 (Box 24)
    - Political economy 2: Economics (George Dowie) 1915 (Box 24)
    - Astronomy 2a: Elementary astronomy (Ralph Curtiss), 1914 (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous lecture notes (including Harmony, German, Mineralogy) (Box 24)
  - Diary 1912 (Box 24)
    (especially Fall 1912 semester)
  - Detroit Central High School notebooks, papers, examinations, etc. circa 1900-1910 (Box 24)
- Harry B. Weber papers
  The papers of Harry B. Weber, William Weber's eldest son and business partner, also consists primarily of correspondence and course class notebooks for University of Michigan classes and notes on special lectures. The notebooks include courses taught by Earle. W. Dow, Frederick Taylor, Claude Van Tyne, Claude Hussey and Filibert Roth and special lectures by Henry Carter Adams, Robert Mark Wenly, Jacob Reighard and Edward Kraus. The Correspondence includes letters from Harry's student days as well as later professional life. Much of his business correspondence is filed in the William C. Weber Correspondence files.
  - Correspondence 1906-1934, 20 folders (Box 25)
  - Class notes and examinations
    - History 1: Europe, 4th-13th centuries (Earle W. Dow) 1908 (Box 25)
    - History 14 and 15: Political and constitutional history of the U.S. (Claude Van Tyne) 1908-1909 (Box 25)
    - History 45: History of the U.S. from beginning of the Civil War (Frederick Paxton) 1909 (Box 25)
    - Political economy: Production and exchange (Fred Taylor) 1908 (Box 25)
    - Astronomy 1: The solar system (William Hussey); and Rhetoric 2: Composition and rhetoric (Clarence Morrill) 1908 (Box 25)
    - Mathematics 1: Plane trigonometry and algebra (Joseph Markley); and Chemistry: General and inorganic chemistry (S. Lawrence Bigelow) 1907 (Box 25)
    - French 1: Elementary French (Hugo Thieme) 1908 (Box 25)
    - Forestry 1: Introductory forestry (Filibert Roth), 1908; and Physics 1: General physics (John Reed) 1907 (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous lecture notes (including Henry Carter Adams "Interstate Commerce Commission"; Robert Mark Wenley "Philosophy"; Edward Kraus "Mineralogy"; Jacob Reighard "Evolution and Darwin"; Forestry; Panama Canal; Landscape gardening; Theology; Cobalt) (Box 25)
  - Johan C. Weber will, 1889 (Box 25)
- Photographs
  Photographs are found in Boxes 26-30 and one outsize volume. Included are photos of the bridge and tunnel and Weber's Windsor properties, as well as a large file of glass negatives taken during family vacations in Upper Michigan, Ontario, and Quebec.
  - Photographic Prints
    - Aerial views of Windsor and Detroit (Box 26)
    - Ambassador Bridge under construction (Box 26)
    - Detroit-Windsor Tunnel construction (Box 26)
    - Houses (Box 26)
    - Portraits
      - William C. Weber (Box 26)
      - Erwin and Harry Weber (Box 26)
      - Miscellaneous, most unidentified, from albums (Box 26)
    - Relatives and friends in Germany (Box 26)
    - Sinfonia fraternity and miscellaneous University of Michigan student activities (Box 26)
    - Holmes Literary Society album, 1909 (Box 26)
    - Albums, 2 volumes (Box 26)
    - Photograph album (Volume 12)
      [12]
  - Glass negatives
    (scattered cellulose negatives)
    - Saguenay trip August 1907, 140 items (Box 27)
      [views of Niagara Falls and vicinity, St. Lawrence River, Saguenay River, Quebec, New York State and City]
    - Marquette and Ishpeming 1907, 66 items (Box 28)
      [views of quarries, mines, and mining activities, furnaces]
    - Detroit 1907-1909, 41 items (Box 28)
      [Belle Isle, Palmer Woods, Eight Mile Road, Weber, Behr, and Gies families]
    - Duluth trip August 1910, 33 items (Box 28)
      [includes scenes of Portage Canal and Houghton, Hancock, Mackinac Island, and Marquette, Michigan]
    - 1912-1913, 16 items (Box 29)
      [family excursions, Belle Isle, country scenes]
    - Georgian Bay, 57 items (Box 29)
    - Lakes, rivers, and forest scenes, 59 items (Box 29)
      [includes scenes of Huron Mountain Club]
    - Excursion May-June 1907, 79 items (Box 30)
      [McCormick Lodge, Huron Mountain Club, camping, falls, Camp Island]
    - Miscellaneous, 20 items (Box 30)
    - Unidentified, 32 items (Box 30)
- Maps